<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Michael Senter on Michael Senter</title>
    <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Michael Senter on Michael Senter</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Michael Senter</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Life in a Day - Anniversary</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/post/20170724_lifeinaday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/post/20170724_lifeinaday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;July 24th, 2010 was a normal day for most people. They got up in the morning,
brushed their teeth and went about their business. For some, it may have been the
best day of their life. For others, the worst. Some
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.prb.org/pdf10/10wpds_eng.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;6.9 billion people&lt;/a&gt;
were alive on that day. Each with their own story, their own fears, their own
dreams and challenges. Some were lucky and spent the day driving their
sports car for fun or relaxing on a yacht. Others desperately tried to find food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one little fact that makes this day special. People around the world
filmed their day. Not in the way we take snapshots with our cellphones for
ourselves. They filmed in order to share their life with the world. In 2010
one of my favorite directors, Ridley Scott, anounced a collaboration with Scott
Free Productions to create a very unique documentary. They would encourage
people all over the world to film their day. To make sure even the poorest
countries could participate, they arranged funds to send cameras to poor nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/6/64/Lifeinaday_2011.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so thousands of people from 192 countries created footage of July 24th, 2010.
The producers went over all the videos and collected them into a &amp;ldquo;day.&amp;rdquo; It starts with
footage from when it&amp;rsquo;s still dark in the wee-hours of the morning. It goes through
the day until midnight. Despite being crowd-sourced it fits together surprisingly
well. I love the movie because it shows that even though people around the world
do live each in their own little worlds with distinct language, dress, food, and
culture, we all share a common humanity that is often lost. It&amp;rsquo;s difficutl to
realize the complextity inherent in all strangers and we often take mental shortcuts
when dealing with people. To me, this movie gives hope for humanity. It gives
me hope that we can all work together to provide a better world for ourselves and
our descendents. I highly recommend watching this movie, especially
if you haven&amp;rsquo;t seen it before. You can watch the whole thing on YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/JaFVr_cJJIY&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I really hope we can make a 25th or 50th anniversary edition in the future. It
would be fun to compare how life has changed by then.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Math Bio in Utah - 2017</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/post/20170723_conferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/post/20170723_conferences/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m back in North Carolina after an exciting week of conferences and meeting
many new people working in mathematical biology throughout the world. It
started with the Utah math bio alumni meeting in honor of Jim Keener&amp;rsquo;s 70th
birthday, which I briefly mentioned last week, and was followed by SMB&amp;rsquo;s annual
meeting. Both were held in Salt Lake City, UT. I really love being back in Utah,
even if it&amp;rsquo;s only for a little while. It was a great place to live. And the
humidity&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;d take 100 F in Utah over 85 F in North Carolina any day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;math-bio-alumni&#34;&gt;Math Bio Alumni&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dmsenter89.github.io/img/blog/utah2017/keener_logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was excited to see talks by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.math.ucdavis.edu/~guy/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bob Guy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.math.ucdavis.edu/~tjlewis//&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tim Lewis&lt;/a&gt;.
I heard of them in lab meetings but hadn&amp;rsquo;t met them before. By chance I wound up sitting
next to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.webpages.uidaho.edu/~snuismer/Nuismer_Lab/people.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Andrew Basinski&lt;/a&gt; on Friday.
After a brief &amp;ldquo;you look familiar&amp;rdquo; we recognized each other; back when I was an undergraduate at the
University of Utah he was the TA for a math bio class I took from Fred Adler. He used to work
on ants and now is working on the dynamics of vaccines that can spread much like a disease,
except instead of making you sick they keep you from becoming sick. That was
pretty exciting. I got to know a number of people from
&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=X8QTUKYAAAAJ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Karin Leiderman&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; group,
namely graduate students &lt;a href=&#34;https://ndanes.wordpress.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Nicholas Danes&lt;/a&gt;
and Michael Kelley, and undergraduate Alison Wallbank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dmsenter89.github.io/img/blog/utah2017/lakesolitude.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lake Solitude&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the conference officially ended on Saturday, Sunday still had activities.
We went to the Math Biology Research and Reatreat Center, aka the Keener cabin,
in Big Cottonwood Canyon. From there we went on a 3 mile hike to Lake
Solitude (pictured above). We concluded with a BBQ at the cabin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;smb-2017&#34;&gt;SMB 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to say I am now quite a fan of SMB meetings. This week was amazing.
I&amp;rsquo;m already excited for next year&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href=&#34;http://conferences.science.unsw.edu.au/SMB2018/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SMB in Sydney&lt;/a&gt;.
A fun experience here has been my starting to recognize names and faces of
people I&amp;rsquo;ve met at previous conferences. It&amp;rsquo;s a nice feeling.
It nakes me feel more like I belong and less like a student out of his league.
We had a nice group from UNC there, especially several of Greg Forest&amp;rsquo;s people:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=KcluNRsAAAAJ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jia Zhao&lt;/a&gt;,
a postdoc starting at Utah State this fall; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/timothy-wessler-48795a135/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tim Wessler&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/caitlinhult/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Caitlin Hult&lt;/a&gt;, graduate students of Dr. Forest starting their
postdocs at Minnesota this fall; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Kelsey_Gasior&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kelsey Gasior&lt;/a&gt;,
a postdoc in Biology who has been collaborating with Dr. Forest&amp;rsquo;s team on some multiphase
modeling in fungi. &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Nmz0gHAAAAAJ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jay Newby&lt;/a&gt;,
one of Dr. Forest&amp;rsquo;s postdocs I
hadn&amp;rsquo;t previously met was likewise present. Of course my advisor Laura Miller and
labmate Anne Talkington were here as well. We also saw Maggie Myers again. She&amp;rsquo;s
an undergraduate researcher from Rhodes College who is also associated with St.
Jude Children&amp;rsquo;s Research Hospital. She gave a talk at BAMM
this May and will be applying to graduate school this fall. Reminded me of my first
trip to a conference - SIAM CSE in 2015. Although mine didn&amp;rsquo;t have me travel out
of state and
I only went once, I had a really good experience. It was also good to see
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/alexanderphoover/home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Alex Hoover&lt;/a&gt; again. He&amp;rsquo;s a
former graduate student of my advisor, Laura Miller, who is currently a postdoc
at Tulane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monday morning started great for me with the session on
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.utah.edu/~smb2017/MS4.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;neuromechanical locomotion&lt;/a&gt;.
Several people from the
Tulane workshop in January were there. One talk that I especially enjoyed was the one
by &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Wf_rspwAAAAJ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Eatai Roth&lt;/a&gt;, who
discussed moth&amp;rsquo;s handling of sensory feedback, specifically visual disturbance
versus mechanical disturbance felt through the proposcis.
The afternoon I went to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.utah.edu/~smb2017/CS4.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;cell biology&lt;/a&gt;
session. My favorite talk of that session was probably Richard Buckalow&amp;rsquo;s talk.
The poster session was held on Monday evening at the Natural History Museum.
It was a fantastic setup in the museum&amp;rsquo;s foyer. We had dinner and open wine &amp;amp;
beer bar. I don&amp;rsquo;t know
the exact number, but there were over 100 poster presenters present! It was
a wonderful experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.utah.edu/~smb2017/CS5.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;evolution and plant ecology&lt;/a&gt; session
was held on Tuesday morning.
I was particularily impressed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=TCju1A4AAAAJ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Michael Cortez&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;http://sydney.edu.au/science/people/peter.kim.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Peter Kim&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; talks. Peter&amp;rsquo;s
talk focused on a model for the &amp;ldquo;grandmother effect&amp;rdquo;, which was an interesting
model.
Tusday we only had the morning sessions and a plenary, while the afternoon
was reserved for field trips and exploration. For that reason we had a simpler
boxed lunch that day, which turned out in my opinion to have actually been the
best lunch of the week. It was really simple too: a mozzarella &amp;amp; tomato sandwich.
The bread was excellent, the cheese sumptuous, and the tomatos just marvelous.
After lunch my lab, including former member Alex Hoover, went on a hike.
We wanted to go up to the &amp;ldquo;Living room&amp;rdquo; but we took a detour and wound up at a
different spot instead. Despite that, the sunset up on the mountains was just
beautiful. The header image for this post was taken during that hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dmsenter89.github.io/img/blog/utah2017/mountainside.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a great session on the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.utah.edu/~smb2017/MS19.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mathematical modeling of honeybees&lt;/a&gt;.
on Wednesday. It was quite fascinating. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t heard any recent news
regarding hive collapses since it&amp;rsquo;s been in
the news a few years ago, so I was interested in hearing what has been going on
with this.  The session started off strong with
&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=1urBjqAAAAAJ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mary Myerscough&lt;/a&gt;
discussing some of her ODE models on
hive death. While only a minor part of the talk, I appreciated her pointing out
that bees may have nutritional deficits due to being surrounded by monocultures.
While it seems very reasonable and quite obvious once you point it out, I have
never actually actively thought about bee nutrition. So that was
fun. She is a very good speaker and her talk was quite engaging.
I also really enjoyed two talks from the afternoon
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.utah.edu/~smb2017/MS26.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ecology and Crime&lt;/a&gt; session:
Joanna Sooknanan and Donna Comissiong discussed the crime problem in
Trinidad and Tobego utilizing a modified SIR model to describe gang
dynamics. They spent quite a bit of time describing the rise of crime and
especially gang violence in Trinidad &amp;amp; Tobego. It reminded me of what I had
read on the rise of crime in the US several decades ago. Like the US earlier,
politicians in Trinidad &amp;amp; Tobego felt that a good way to address the rise in
crime would be by substantially increasing prison sentences, a method of dealing
with crime that ignores problems associated with increased prison terms such as
gang recruitment in prison and the difficulty of adjusting to a &amp;ldquo;normal life&amp;rdquo;
after release. The talk by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www-scf.usc.edu/~saramarm/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Sara Mc Carthy&lt;/a&gt;
was also quite fascinating. She discussed game theoretic approaches to
security challenges, with applications to illegal logging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual banquet and dance was held Wednesday evening. I loved it. They had
great food, but I mostly enjoyed the dancing. I personally love ballroom dancing
and I had the good fortune to dance with some fun fellow mathematicians. Good
times were had :) .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though Thursday was the last day of the conference we had some great
talks and spirits remained high. I thoroughly enjoyed both plenary talks,
both Dushoff&amp;rsquo;s discussion of epidemiology and Mimi Kohl&amp;rsquo;s discussion of
microorganisms swimming in turbulent flow. I had previously been to one of her
talks so I was quite excited to see her plenary. She definitely didn&amp;rsquo;t disappoint.
She was very animated and had some cool pictures and great science. Alex
Hoover gave his talk in the morning fluid session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I have to say I met a lot of great people and I had a tremendous amount
of fun. I can&amp;rsquo;t wait for SMB 2018!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MeshmerizeMe: A Tool for the Creation of Curvilinear Meshes for Immersed Boundary Simulations</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/smb_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/smb_2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chalk Talks and Plots</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/post/20170716_chalk_talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/post/20170716_chalk_talks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The past few days I was at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.utah.edu/research/mathbio/workshops/UtahAlumConference.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Utah Math Bio Alumni Conference&lt;/a&gt;.
It was great being back at my &lt;em&gt;alma mater&lt;/em&gt; surrounded by so many talented
mathematicians and scientists, but more on that next week when I&amp;rsquo;ll write about
my conference experience (I&amp;rsquo;ll also be at SMB this week). What I want to write
about today are some thoughts I&amp;rsquo;ve had on chalk talks. Prior to their talks a lot
of presenters took a few minutes to reminisce about their experiences with Utah math bio.
The quality of physiology group meetings came up several times. At one point, someone
(I think it was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.ubc.ca/~cytryn/index.shtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Eric Cytrynbaum&lt;/a&gt;)
mentioned how it was difficult nowadays to get students to use the board during
group meetings when everyone has a laptop and uses powerpoints and computer-generated
plots. That got me thinking and wondering when I&amp;rsquo;ve had my last &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; chalk talk.
And it&amp;rsquo;s been a while. It&amp;rsquo;s definitely true in my experience that we&amp;rsquo;ve become
very reliant on powerpoints and beamer presentations. And I have to say I miss chalk
talks. When I was a senior at Utah I took an intro to applied math course
with Dr. Cherkaev that required us to present a final project on a topic of our
choosing. I remember being the only one in the course &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; using a powerpoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like chalk talks and I think being good at chalk talks is a
great skill to have. And it&amp;rsquo;s especially important for graduate students. We don&amp;rsquo;t
have a lot of papers out yet, with us being early in our career and all. But
we have ideas and enthusiasm. Actively writing your work down while you discuss it
with peers is a great way to communicate that enthusiasm. And
this is frankly one area where I feel that pure math students tend to have a leg
up on applied students. Or at least the one&amp;rsquo;s I know. One-on-one meetings with
their advisors tend to involve blackboard work or going over handwritten pages.
Applied students? Open your laptop, show some code and or graphs, what have you.
Not that there is anything wrong with that. It just leads to us having less
practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the appeals of computer aided presentation is that we can use graphs and
images. In science we often have cool images and nice graphs and we love
showing them off. But whether or not it is important to show someone these
particular visuals depends on what we&amp;rsquo;re trying to accomplish.
I&amp;rsquo;m not arguing we should do chalk talks at
conference presentations. I&amp;rsquo;m thinking more of informal settings such as lab meetings
or just getting together with peers in the department lounge. In such informal
situations, what I am generally trying to accomplish is give my peers a high level
overview of what I&amp;rsquo;m currently doing, what challenges I may face and what results
I got. And if I have plots, I don&amp;rsquo;t expect them to notice anything very precise.
In general I&amp;rsquo;m trying to point out some qualitative behavior of interest. And that
frankly does not require me firing up matplotlib or a draft of a paper I&amp;rsquo;m
writing. Qualitative behavior lends itself to back-of-the-envelope plotting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;XKCD is a great example of just how effectivey seemingly &amp;ldquo;crude&amp;rdquo; plots and charts
can be. &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/1319/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is an example:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/automation.png&#34; alt=&#34;XKCD Graph&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gets the point across. Humor in this case, but the same can be done with research.
I&amp;rsquo;m sure most of us have done it at some point; perhaps at a bar on a napkin with
their peers after a conference. And it&amp;rsquo;s exciting and fun. I feel it draws
the audience in more than searching through your phone for some nice plot you made.
Doing this type of presentation more often would be refreshing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MeshmerizeMe: A Tool for the Creation of Curvilinear Meshes for Immersed Boundary Simulations</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/utah_mbalumn_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/utah_mbalumn_2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IBM Geometry Creation</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/project/meshmerizeme/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/project/meshmerizeme/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nickabattista/IB2d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IB2d&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/IBAMR/IBAMR&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IBAMR&lt;/a&gt; are two software packages implementing
the immersed boundary method (see below). These packages model fluid-structure
interaction problems based on user given parameters and geometry. The manual
creation of the initial geometry mesh can be difficult and time consuming,
especially for the complex shapes encountered in biological applications.
Oftentimes we have images of the geometry we wish to explore.
I am developing software to help automate the creation of such CFD meshes for
2D simulations with a file-format suitable for use with IB2d and IBAMR from
images. An initial prototype version is available on
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dmsenter89/MeshmerizeMe&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;. A paper
exploring the use of MeshmerizeMe in conjuction with IB2d for simulations is
in preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;usage&#34;&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MeshmerizeMe needs two input files per experimental geometry: an SVG image file
with the geometry of interest and an input2d file with the experiment parameters.
When selecting an SVG for use with MeshmerizeMe it will automatically look for
the input2d file in the same folder. It will then parse the paths, transform
them into the correct coordinate system and appropriately sample the paths based
on the size of the Cartesian grid set in the input2d file. The geometry will be
exported as a vertex file. This file is readable by both IB2d and IBAMR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SVGs were chosen as the image source as the are an open, text-based format
making them very accesible to work with. They are standardized for web use and
many tools exist for creating and manipulating SVG images. They can be created
from source images such as photographs or scans by means of edge detection tools
and by manually tracing the outline of a shape of interest
Consider optimizing the SVG prior to processing to save time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the current version of MeshmerizeMe only handles a subset of SVG, tools that
optimize the SVG files created by your editor are very useful. Examples of such
software include  &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/svg/svgo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SVGO&lt;/a&gt;, which also offers a
webapp  called &lt;a href=&#34;https://jakearchibald.github.io/svgomg/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SVGOMG&lt;/a&gt;.
Another software is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/RazrFalcon/svgcleaner&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;svgcleaner&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ibm-background&#34;&gt;IBM Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One aspect of computational fluid dynamics is the investigation of&lt;br /&gt;
fluid-structure interactions. One method developed for the study of such
interactions is the immersed boundary method (IBM) developed by Peskin&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
It is well known that fluids can be studied from both a Eulerian and a
Lagrangian view. The IBM combines these - the domain of the problem is resolved
as a Cartesian grid on which Eulerian equations are solved for fluid velocity
and pressure. In the case of Newtonian fluids the incompressible Navier-Stokes
equations comprising of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ \rho  \left( \frac{\partial \mathbf{u}}{\partial t} + \mathbf{u} \cdot \nabla \mathbf{u} \right)  = - \nabla \mathbf{p} + \mu \nabla^2 \mathbf{u} + \mathbf{f}$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$\nabla \cdot \mathbf{u} = 0$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;need to be solved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The immersed structures are modeled as fibers in the form of parametric
curves $X(s,t)$, where $s$ is a parameter and $t$ is time. The fiber experiences
force distributions $F(s,t)$, and we can derive the force the fiber exerts on
the fluid from the momentum equation. For the fibers we then solve&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$\mathbf{f} = \int_\Gamma \mathbf{F}(s,t)\,\delta\left(\mathbf{x}-\mathbf{X}(s,t)\right)\,ds$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$\frac{\partial \mathbf{X}}{\partial t} = \int_\Omega \mathbf{u}(\mathbf{x},t)\, \delta \left( \mathbf{x}-\mathbf{X}(s,t)\right)\,d\mathbf{x}.$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, $\Gamma$ is the immersed structure and $\Omega$ is the fluid domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The immersed structures are discretized not on a Cartesian grid but on a
separate Lagrangian grid on the fiber itself. Of import to CFD software users
is that the initial discretization of the immersed structure has to be
supplied by the user. While this is not too difficult for simple geometries,
the often complex structures encountered in mathematical biology can present
a significant time investment. This is the part where MeshmerizeMe comes in
handy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Charles S Peskin. 2002. &amp;ldquo;The immersed boundary method.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Acta numerica&lt;/em&gt; 11:479-517.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Filming Thrips with Vishwa</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/post/20170702-filming-with-vishwa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/post/20170702-filming-with-vishwa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past month has been rather exciting due to a visit by OSU graduate student
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appliedfluidslab.org/personnel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Vishwa Teja Kasoju&lt;/a&gt;. He is a student
in the Mechanical &amp;amp; Aerospace engineering PhD program as part of
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appliedfluidslab.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Santhanakrishnan&amp;rsquo;s lab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vishwa visited both UNC and Duke to get some footage of thrips flight and
Mantis shrimp escape behaviors. My undergraduate student Kristen Armel and I
assisted Vishwa in some of his thrips collecting and filming. It was a good
learning experience for us, as we learned how to work with the high speed cameras
we have on-site. We had good luck finding thrips around campus, escpecially a
day after it rained. Luckily there were plenty of rainy days in June, so we
had no shortage of specimen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny Insect Flight</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/project/tiny-insects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/project/tiny-insects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Winged insects are taxonomically diverse and inhabit virtually every terrestrial
ecosystem on our planet. They range in size from the most minute insects, barely
visible to the naked eye, to those with wingspans greater than 7 inches - larger
than the palm of an adult human! With such diversity, insects provide a plethora
 of model organisms for investigating flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students of biology are familiar with the fact that small bacteria tend to move
differently than fish swim for example. This is because a swimming motion is not
effective in moving you forward when you&amp;rsquo;re as small as a bacterium. But flagella
and celia will in fact move you forward effectively at that size. This difference
in behavior has to do with how the organism in question experiences the relative
effects of inertial and viscous forces. One way of quantifying the relative
importance of these effects is with the dimensionless quantity known as the
&lt;em&gt;Reynolds number&lt;/em&gt;; it is given by
$$\mathrm{Re}= \frac{\rho u L}{\mu},$$
where $\rho$ is the density of the fluid&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in which the organism is moving, $u$ is
the velocity of the fluid with respect to the organism, $L$ is the &amp;ldquo;characteristic
length&amp;rdquo; of the organism, and $\mu$ is the dynamic viscosity of the fluid. We and
many of the animals that we are familiar with from every day life live in a &amp;ldquo;high
Reynolds number world.&amp;rdquo; When we say high, we mean a value of Re in the thousands
and tens of thousands and higher. Bacteria on the other hand live in a low
Reynolds number world, with values on the order of $\mathrm{Re} \ll 1$. The
intermediate Reynolds number world is less well studied, and that&amp;rsquo;s where some
interesting stuff happens!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very small insects, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thrips&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;thrips&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fairyfly&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;fairyflies&lt;/a&gt;, live in the intermediate
Reynolds number world. While larger insects typically create lift
by creating a leading edge vortex that remains attached to their wings, while a
trailing edge vortex is created and shed from the wing with each stroke. The tiny
insects on the other hand shed neither their trailing nor leading edge vortices,
and instead engage in what is known as clap-and-fling
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Insect_flight#Aerodynamics&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;cf. here for some details&lt;/a&gt;).
Another interesting aspect of the flight of the smallest fliers is that their
wings show interesting adaptations. Most of us are familiar with the way
bee wings look. Even fruitflies have a very similar wing structure. Very tiny
fliers on the other hand will have relatively small wings with large bristles
attached to them, as in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dmsenter89.github.io/img/thrips.png&#34; alt=&#34;alternative text for search engines&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When gathering footage for previous work on clap-and-fling
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1242/jeb.084897&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Santhanakrishnan et al, 2014&lt;/a&gt;), we
also happened to come across footage showing parachuting behavior. Active flight
is energetically costly, especially if you want to go far. Passive flight
behaviors are an integral part of long-distance travel; just think of large
birds you may see circling on convection currents in the air. My work is on
trying to understand the aerodynamics of such passive flight behaviors in tiny
insects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Mathematically, we can treat air as a fluid.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Tiny Insects and Investigating Passive Dispersal</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/bcb_new_student_talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2017 21:25:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/bcb_new_student_talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aerodynamics of parachuting in tiny insects</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/bamm-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/bamm-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mean first passage time in a thermally fluctuating viscoelastic fluid</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/publication/mfpt_thermal_fluctuation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/publication/mfpt_thermal_fluctuation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aerodynamics of parachuting in tiny insects</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/tulane-winter-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/tulane-winter-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Model of Muscle Response to Neuronal Spike Activity</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/facm-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/facm-2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mean Squared Displacement and Mean First Passage Time in Fluids with Memory</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/siam-cse-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/talk/siam-cse-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
