<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thoughts on Michael Senter</title>
    <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/tags/thoughts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Thoughts on Michael Senter</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Michael Senter</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/thoughts/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Chalk Talks and Plots</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/post/20170716_chalk_talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/post/20170716_chalk_talks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The past few days I was at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.utah.edu/research/mathbio/workshops/UtahAlumConference.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Utah Math Bio Alumni Conference&lt;/a&gt;.
It was great being back at my &lt;em&gt;alma mater&lt;/em&gt; surrounded by so many talented
mathematicians and scientists, but more on that next week when I&amp;rsquo;ll write about
my conference experience (I&amp;rsquo;ll also be at SMB this week). What I want to write
about today are some thoughts I&amp;rsquo;ve had on chalk talks. Prior to their talks a lot
of presenters took a few minutes to reminisce about their experiences with Utah math bio.
The quality of physiology group meetings came up several times. At one point, someone
(I think it was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.ubc.ca/~cytryn/index.shtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Eric Cytrynbaum&lt;/a&gt;)
mentioned how it was difficult nowadays to get students to use the board during
group meetings when everyone has a laptop and uses powerpoints and computer-generated
plots. That got me thinking and wondering when I&amp;rsquo;ve had my last &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; chalk talk.
And it&amp;rsquo;s been a while. It&amp;rsquo;s definitely true in my experience that we&amp;rsquo;ve become
very reliant on powerpoints and beamer presentations. And I have to say I miss chalk
talks. When I was a senior at Utah I took an intro to applied math course
with Dr. Cherkaev that required us to present a final project on a topic of our
choosing. I remember being the only one in the course &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; using a powerpoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like chalk talks and I think being good at chalk talks is a
great skill to have. And it&amp;rsquo;s especially important for graduate students. We don&amp;rsquo;t
have a lot of papers out yet, with us being early in our career and all. But
we have ideas and enthusiasm. Actively writing your work down while you discuss it
with peers is a great way to communicate that enthusiasm. And
this is frankly one area where I feel that pure math students tend to have a leg
up on applied students. Or at least the one&amp;rsquo;s I know. One-on-one meetings with
their advisors tend to involve blackboard work or going over handwritten pages.
Applied students? Open your laptop, show some code and or graphs, what have you.
Not that there is anything wrong with that. It just leads to us having less
practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the appeals of computer aided presentation is that we can use graphs and
images. In science we often have cool images and nice graphs and we love
showing them off. But whether or not it is important to show someone these
particular visuals depends on what we&amp;rsquo;re trying to accomplish.
I&amp;rsquo;m not arguing we should do chalk talks at
conference presentations. I&amp;rsquo;m thinking more of informal settings such as lab meetings
or just getting together with peers in the department lounge. In such informal
situations, what I am generally trying to accomplish is give my peers a high level
overview of what I&amp;rsquo;m currently doing, what challenges I may face and what results
I got. And if I have plots, I don&amp;rsquo;t expect them to notice anything very precise.
In general I&amp;rsquo;m trying to point out some qualitative behavior of interest. And that
frankly does not require me firing up matplotlib or a draft of a paper I&amp;rsquo;m
writing. Qualitative behavior lends itself to back-of-the-envelope plotting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;XKCD is a great example of just how effectivey seemingly &amp;ldquo;crude&amp;rdquo; plots and charts
can be. &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/1319/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is an example:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/automation.png&#34; alt=&#34;XKCD Graph&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gets the point across. Humor in this case, but the same can be done with research.
I&amp;rsquo;m sure most of us have done it at some point; perhaps at a bar on a napkin with
their peers after a conference. And it&amp;rsquo;s exciting and fun. I feel it draws
the audience in more than searching through your phone for some nice plot you made.
Doing this type of presentation more often would be refreshing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
