<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Elizabeth Senter, MPH | Michael&#39;s Site</title>
    <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/author/elizabeth-senter-mph/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dmsenter89.github.io/author/elizabeth-senter-mph/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Elizabeth Senter, MPH</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 10:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dmsenter89.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Elizabeth Senter, MPH</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/author/elizabeth-senter-mph/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Family History And Chronic Medical Conditions Associated With Sudden Death Among Working Age Adults</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/publication/doshi-2022-family-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/publication/doshi-2022-family-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sudden death accounts for 10% of deaths in the United States. Prior research has
focused on sudden death in older victims, leaving much unknown about risk factors for younger,
working age adults. Compared to older adults, younger adults may be more vulnerable to genetic factors.
Understanding age related differences in sudden death risk factors may guide future prevention efforts,
as the factors contributing to sudden death in younger patients may warrant different types of prevention
than those affecting older adults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 2013-2015, out-of-hospital deaths among adults aged 18-64 in Wake County, NC were screened and adjudicated
to identify 306 sudden death victims. A comparison group of 1,113 patients matched for age, gender, and residence
was formed by randomly sampling individuals from the Carolina Data Warehouse. For sudden death victims and controls,
the prevalence of sudden death risk factors, comprising comorbidities, mental illnesses, and family history variables,
were assessed in three age groups (18-41, 42-54, and 55-64 years old). Hypothesis testing was conducted for each
variable across all pairwise combinations of age groups using an unpaired, two-sample proportion Z-test with $p&amp;lt;0.05$
as statistically significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of the variables analyzed were more prevalent in younger sudden death victims compared to older victims.
However, family history variables were largely missing (&amp;gt;80%) compared to comorbidities and mental illnesses (&amp;lt;10%),
with younger adults being disproportionately affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underreporting of family history in medical records leaves younger adults as a poorly understood subset of sudden death
victims who are currently unable to be appropriately screened for lifesaving preventive measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;public-health-implications&#34;&gt;Public Health Implications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Better family history documentation may identify younger adults at higher risk of sudden death, allowing more
comprehensive population level screening and implementation of prevention measures appropriate for addressing genetic
factors instead of the environmental factors more common in older adults.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Former Incarceration As A Risk Factor For COVID-19 Associated Sudden Death</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/publication/raghunathan-2022-incarceration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/publication/raghunathan-2022-incarceration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States, former incarceration is a risk factor for chronic conditions and sudden death (SD)
due to poor healthcare continuity after release and lack of community support. During the COVID-19 pandemic,
all-cause mortality increased, and preexisting risk factors and social limitations of having an incarceration
history were exacerbated. We hypothesized that sudden deaths among the formerly incarcerated increased during
the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;North Carolina death certificates from pre-COVID-19 (2014) and during the COVID-19 pandemic (2020) were screened
for presumed SD. Individuals were excluded based on age ($&amp;lt;18$ or $&amp;gt;65$), violent or expected deaths, and deaths
in hospitals or care facilities. Deaths were matched to the North Carolina Department of Public Safety Criminal
Offender Database for a history of incarceration. ICD-10 codes for hypertension, diabetes, chronic respiratory
disease, obesity, mental health, and substance abuse were extracted from the top four causes of death on the death
certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found no significant difference in the prevalence of former incarceration in SD victims from 2014 to 2020.
In 2020, the odds of substance abuse among SD victims with a history of incarceration were significantly greater
compared to those without a history of incarceration (OR (95CI): 2.29 (1.91-2.73)). The odds of substance abuse among
the formerly incarcerated were greater in 2020 SD victims compared to 2014 SD victims (2.29 (1.76-2.99)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sudden death among the formerly incarcerated did not significantly increase during the COVID-19 pandemic.
Increased public health funding may have limited the expected effects of COVID-19 on rates of sudden death in formerly
incarcerated individuals. However, the formerly incarcerated appear to be vulnerable to dying of sudden death associated
with substance abuse in 2020. Improving statewide transition programs targeting substance abuse counseling during
healthcare crises should improve health outcomes and reduce the rate of sudden death among the formerly incarcerated
population.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Housing Insecurity: Effects on Sudden Death and Interaction with Mental Illness</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/publication/vrooman-2022-housing-insecurity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/publication/vrooman-2022-housing-insecurity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Housing insecurity is a powerful social determinant of health that is associated with increased all-cause mortality.
The health consequences of and contributors to housing insecurity are poorly studied, which makes preventative care
elusive for this population. In order to address these issues, we assessed the prevalence of housing insecurity
among sudden death victims and examined its relationship to sudden death, mental illness, and clinical comorbidities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 1 March 2013 to 28 February 2015, out-of-hospital deaths in Wake County, North Carolina, were screened and adjudicated
to identify 399 sudden deaths among residents between the ages of 18 and 64. A control sample of 1,101 living patients were
generated by randomly sampling for age, gender, and Wake County residence from the Carolina Data Warehouse for Health.
Housing status was abstracted from clinical records from sudden death victims and controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Housing insecurity was documented in 28 (7.1%) of victims and 47 (4.3%) of controls (OR(95CI): 1.71(1.05-3.2)). This difference
remained significant after adjusting for hypertension, age, and diabetes. However, when additionally adjusting for depression,
anxiety, alcohol abuse, substance abuse, schizophrenia, and bipolar disorder, the increased prevalence of housing insecurity
in the sudden death group became insignificant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Housing insecure individuals experience a higher burden of sudden death than housing secure individuals. Mental illness
appears to confound the relationship between housing insecurity and sudden death. Treating underlying mental illness may
be a path towards specializing clinical care to optimize health outcomes for housing insecure individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;clinical-implications&#34;&gt;Clinical Implications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optimize health outcomes for housing insecure individuals by acknowledging that housing insecurity appears to be a risk
factor for sudden death - a relationship complicated by mental illness.  Patients with housing insecurity should be screened
for mental illness, and treatment and referral to a mental illness specialist should be considered.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
