<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Movies on Michael Senter</title>
    <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/tags/movies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Movies on Michael Senter</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Michael Senter</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/movies/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Life in a Day - Anniversary</title>
      <link>https://dmsenter89.github.io/post/20170724_lifeinaday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dmsenter89.github.io/post/20170724_lifeinaday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;July 24th, 2010 was a normal day for most people. They got up in the morning,
brushed their teeth and went about their business. For some, it may have been the
best day of their life. For others, the worst. Some
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.prb.org/pdf10/10wpds_eng.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;6.9 billion people&lt;/a&gt;
were alive on that day. Each with their own story, their own fears, their own
dreams and challenges. Some were lucky and spent the day driving their
sports car for fun or relaxing on a yacht. Others desperately tried to find food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one little fact that makes this day special. People around the world
filmed their day. Not in the way we take snapshots with our cellphones for
ourselves. They filmed in order to share their life with the world. In 2010
one of my favorite directors, Ridley Scott, anounced a collaboration with Scott
Free Productions to create a very unique documentary. They would encourage
people all over the world to film their day. To make sure even the poorest
countries could participate, they arranged funds to send cameras to poor nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/6/64/Lifeinaday_2011.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so thousands of people from 192 countries created footage of July 24th, 2010.
The producers went over all the videos and collected them into a &amp;ldquo;day.&amp;rdquo; It starts with
footage from when it&amp;rsquo;s still dark in the wee-hours of the morning. It goes through
the day until midnight. Despite being crowd-sourced it fits together surprisingly
well. I love the movie because it shows that even though people around the world
do live each in their own little worlds with distinct language, dress, food, and
culture, we all share a common humanity that is often lost. It&amp;rsquo;s difficutl to
realize the complextity inherent in all strangers and we often take mental shortcuts
when dealing with people. To me, this movie gives hope for humanity. It gives
me hope that we can all work together to provide a better world for ourselves and
our descendents. I highly recommend watching this movie, especially
if you haven&amp;rsquo;t seen it before. You can watch the whole thing on YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/JaFVr_cJJIY&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I really hope we can make a 25th or 50th anniversary edition in the future. It
would be fun to compare how life has changed by then.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
